<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-27T22:54:54+01:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sandra Müller</title><entry><title type="html">(with Y. Hayut) Perfect Subtree Property for Weakly Compact Cardinals</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/publication/published/richterv844/loreal/2022/11/17/PaperPSPweaklycompact.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="(with Y. Hayut) Perfect Subtree Property for Weakly Compact Cardinals" /><published>2022-11-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/publication/published/richterv844/loreal/2022/11/17/PaperPSPweaklycompact</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/publication/published/richterv844/loreal/2022/11/17/PaperPSPweaklycompact.html">&lt;p&gt;Israel Journal of Mathematics. Appeared online. &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11856-022-2385-4&quot;&gt;DOI: 10.1007/s11856-022-2385-4.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1910.05159.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1910.05159&quot;&gt;arXiv.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a data-toggle=&quot;collapse&quot; href=&quot;javascript:toggle('bibHM19');&quot; class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Bibtex.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display:none&quot; id=&quot;bibHM19&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;collapse&quot;&gt; @ARTICLE{HM19,
   AUTHOR= {Y. Hayut and S. Müller},
   TITLE= {Perfect subtree property for weakly compact cardinals},
   JOURNAL={Israel Journal of Mathematics},
   VOLUME = {},
   ISSUE = {},
   YEAR = {2022},
   PAGES = {},
   EPRINT = {1910.05159},
   DOI = {10.1007/s11856-022-2385-4}}&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We investigate the consistency strength of the statement: $\kappa$ is weakly compact and there is no tree on $\kappa$ with exactly $\kappa^{+}$ many branches. We show that this statement fails strongly (in the sense that there is a sealed tree with exactly $\kappa^{+}$ many branches) if there is no inner model with a Woodin cardinal. Moreover, we show that for a weakly compact cardinal $\kappa$ the nonexistence of a tree on $\kappa$ with exactly $\kappa^{+}$ many branches and, in particular, the Perfect Subtree Property for $\kappa$, implies the consistency of $AD_{\mathbb{R}} + DC$.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="published" /><category term="RichterV844" /><category term="LOREAL" /><summary type="html">Israel Journal of Mathematics. Appeared online. DOI: 10.1007/s11856-022-2385-4. PDF. arXiv. Bibtex. @ARTICLE{HM19, AUTHOR= {Y. Hayut and S. Müller}, TITLE= {Perfect subtree property for weakly compact cardinals}, JOURNAL={Israel Journal of Mathematics}, VOLUME = {}, ISSUE = {}, YEAR = {2022}, PAGES = {}, EPRINT = {1910.05159}, DOI = {10.1007/s11856-022-2385-4}}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gdansk Logic Conference - TBA</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/2022/11/16/TalkGdansk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gdansk Logic Conference - TBA" /><published>2022-11-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-11-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/2022/11/16/TalkGdansk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/2022/11/16/TalkGdansk.html">&lt;p&gt;I am invited to give an &lt;b&gt;invited talk&lt;/b&gt; at the first Gdansk Logic Conference, University of Gdansk, Poland, May 5-7, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title and abstract of this talk will be announced in due course.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="upcomingtalk" /><category term="talk" /><category term="invconftalk" /><summary type="html">I am invited to give an invited talk at the first Gdansk Logic Conference, University of Gdansk, Poland, May 5-7, 2023. Title and abstract of this talk will be announced in due course.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">10th Indian Conference on Logic and its Applications (ICLA) - TBA</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/plenary/2022/08/16/TalkICLAIndore.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10th Indian Conference on Logic and its Applications (ICLA) - TBA" /><published>2022-08-16T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-08-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/plenary/2022/08/16/TalkICLAIndore</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/plenary/2022/08/16/TalkICLAIndore.html">&lt;p&gt;I am invited to give an &lt;b&gt;invited talk&lt;/b&gt; at the 10th Indian Conference on Logic and its Applications (ICLA) in Indore, India, March 3-5, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Title and abstract of this talk will be announced in due course.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="upcomingtalk" /><category term="talk" /><category term="invconftalk" /><category term="plenary" /><summary type="html">I am invited to give an invited talk at the 10th Indian Conference on Logic and its Applications (ICLA) in Indore, India, March 3-5, 2023. Title and abstract of this talk will be announced in due course.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">(with P. Schlicht, D. Schrittesser, and T. Weinert) Lebesgue’s density theorem and definable selectors for ideals</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/publication/published/2022/05/02/PaperLebesgueDensity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="(with P. Schlicht, D. Schrittesser, and T. Weinert) Lebesgue’s density theorem and definable selectors for ideals" /><published>2022-05-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-05-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/publication/published/2022/05/02/PaperLebesgueDensity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/publication/published/2022/05/02/PaperLebesgueDensity.html">&lt;p&gt;Israel Journal of Mathematics. Volume 249, May 2022. Pages 501-551.  &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11856-022-2312-8&quot;&gt;DOI: 10.1007/s11856-022-2312-8.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1811.06489.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1811.06489&quot;&gt;arXiv.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a data-toggle=&quot;collapse&quot; href=&quot;javascript:toggle('bibMSSW22');&quot; class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Bibtex.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display:none&quot; id=&quot;bibMSSW22&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;collapse&quot;&gt; @ARTICLE{MSSW22,
   AUTHOR = {S. Müller and P. Schlicht and D. Schrittesser and T. Weinert},
   TITLE = {Lebesgue's density theorem and definable selectors for ideals},
   JOURNAL={Israel Journal of Mathematics},
   VOLUME = {249},
   YEAR = {2022},
   PAGES = {501--551},
   EPRINT = {1811.06489},
   DOI = {10.1007/s11856-022-2312-8} }&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We introduce a notion of density point and prove results analogous to
Lebesgue’s density theorem for various well-known ideals on Cantor
space and Baire space. In fact, we isolate a class of ideals for which
our results hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a contrasting result of independent interest, we
show that there is no reasonably definable selector that chooses
representatives for the equivalence relation on the Borel sets of
having countable symmetric difference. In other words, there is no
notion of density which makes the ideal of countable sets satisfy an
analogue to the density theorem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="published" /><summary type="html">Israel Journal of Mathematics. Volume 249, May 2022. Pages 501-551. DOI: 10.1007/s11856-022-2312-8. PDF. arXiv. Bibtex. @ARTICLE{MSSW22, AUTHOR = {S. Müller and P. Schlicht and D. Schrittesser and T. Weinert}, TITLE = {Lebesgue's density theorem and definable selectors for ideals}, JOURNAL={Israel Journal of Mathematics}, VOLUME = {249}, YEAR = {2022}, PAGES = {501--551}, EPRINT = {1811.06489}, DOI = {10.1007/s11856-022-2312-8} }</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Winter Meeting of the ASL with the JMM - Universally Baire Sets, Determinacy, and Inner Models</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/plenary/2022/02/16/TalkASLJMMBoston.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Winter Meeting of the ASL with the JMM - Universally Baire Sets, Determinacy, and Inner Models" /><published>2022-02-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-02-16T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/plenary/2022/02/16/TalkASLJMMBoston</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/plenary/2022/02/16/TalkASLJMMBoston.html">&lt;p&gt;I am invited to give an &lt;b&gt;invited address&lt;/b&gt; at the 2023 Winter Meeting of the Association for Symbolic Logic with the JMM in Boston, USA, January 4-7, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Universally Baire Sets, Determinacy, and Inner Models&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computing the large cardinal strength of a given statement is one of the key research directions in set theory. Fruitful tools to tackle such questions are given by inner model theory. The study of inner models was initiated by Gödel’s analysis of the constructible universe $L$. Later, it was extended to canonical inner models with large cardinals, e.g., measurable cardinals, strong cardinals or Woodin cardinals, which were introduced and studied by Jensen, Mitchell, Steel, Woodin, Sargsyan, and others. We will outline the role universally Baire sets play in the study of inner models and their connections to determinacy axioms. In particular, we will discuss recent results on $\mathsf{Sealing}$, a formalization due to Woodin of the statement that the theory of the universally Baire sets cannot be changed by forcing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="upcomingtalk" /><category term="talk" /><category term="invconftalk" /><category term="plenary" /><summary type="html">I am invited to give an invited address at the 2023 Winter Meeting of the Association for Symbolic Logic with the JMM in Boston, USA, January 4-7, 2023. Universally Baire Sets, Determinacy, and Inner Models Computing the large cardinal strength of a given statement is one of the key research directions in set theory. Fruitful tools to tackle such questions are given by inner model theory. The study of inner models was initiated by Gödel’s analysis of the constructible universe $L$. Later, it was extended to canonical inner models with large cardinals, e.g., measurable cardinals, strong cardinals or Woodin cardinals, which were introduced and studied by Jensen, Mitchell, Steel, Woodin, Sargsyan, and others. We will outline the role universally Baire sets play in the study of inner models and their connections to determinacy axioms. In particular, we will discuss recent results on $\mathsf{Sealing}$, a formalization due to Woodin of the statement that the theory of the universally Baire sets cannot be changed by forcing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Core Model Seminar - A stationary-tower-free proof of Sealing</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invsemtalk/2022/01/17/TalkCoreModelSeminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Core Model Seminar - A stationary-tower-free proof of Sealing" /><published>2022-01-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invsemtalk/2022/01/17/TalkCoreModelSeminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invsemtalk/2022/01/17/TalkCoreModelSeminar.html">&lt;p&gt;I was invited to give a series of two talks in the Core Model Seminar, an online seminar organized by Ernest Schimmerling and Benjamin Siskind, Carnegie Mellon University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A stationary-tower-free proof of Sealing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sealing is a generic absoluteness principle for the theory of the universally Baire sets of reals introduced by Woodin. It is deeply connected to the Inner Model Program and plays a prominent role in recent advances in inner model theory. Woodin showed in his famous Sealing Theorem that in the presence of a proper class of Woodin cardinals Sealing holds after collapsing a supercompact cardinal. In the first talk, I will outline the importance of Sealing and discuss a new and stationary-tower-free proof of Woodin’s Sealing Theorem that is based on Sargsyan’s and Trang’s proof of Sealing from iterability. In the second talk, I will outline the proof of an extension of the Sealing Theorem that gives models in which Theta is regular. This is joint work with Grigor Sargsyan.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="upcomingtalk" /><category term="talk" /><category term="invsemtalk" /><summary type="html">I was invited to give a series of two talks in the Core Model Seminar, an online seminar organized by Ernest Schimmerling and Benjamin Siskind, Carnegie Mellon University. A stationary-tower-free proof of Sealing Sealing is a generic absoluteness principle for the theory of the universally Baire sets of reals introduced by Woodin. It is deeply connected to the Inner Model Program and plays a prominent role in recent advances in inner model theory. Woodin showed in his famous Sealing Theorem that in the presence of a proper class of Woodin cardinals Sealing holds after collapsing a supercompact cardinal. In the first talk, I will outline the importance of Sealing and discuss a new and stationary-tower-free proof of Woodin’s Sealing Theorem that is based on Sargsyan’s and Trang’s proof of Sealing from iterability. In the second talk, I will outline the proof of an extension of the Sealing Theorem that gives models in which Theta is regular. This is joint work with Grigor Sargsyan.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Baltic Set Theory Seminar - A stationary-tower-free proof of Woodin’s Sealing Theorem</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invsemtalk/2022/01/15/TalkBalticSetTheorySeminar.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baltic Set Theory Seminar - A stationary-tower-free proof of Woodin’s Sealing Theorem" /><published>2022-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invsemtalk/2022/01/15/TalkBalticSetTheorySeminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invsemtalk/2022/01/15/TalkBalticSetTheorySeminar.html">&lt;p&gt;I am invited to give a series of talks in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.impan.pl/~gsargsyan/bsts.html&quot;&gt;Baltic Set Theory Seminar&lt;/a&gt;, an online seminar organized by Grigor Sargsyan. The schedule as well as the zoom link appears on the seminar webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A stationary-tower-free proof of Woodin’s Sealing Theorem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will present a proof of $\mathsf{Sealing}$ from a supercompact and a class of Woodin cardinals using genericity iterations. The proof is joint work with Sargsyan and Wcisło, and builds on the work of Sargsyan-Trang.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="upcomingtalk" /><category term="talk" /><category term="invsemtalk" /><summary type="html">I am invited to give a series of talks in the Baltic Set Theory Seminar, an online seminar organized by Grigor Sargsyan. The schedule as well as the zoom link appears on the seminar webpage. A stationary-tower-free proof of Woodin’s Sealing Theorem I will present a proof of $\mathsf{Sealing}$ from a supercompact and a class of Woodin cardinals using genericity iterations. The proof is joint work with Sargsyan and Wcisło, and builds on the work of Sargsyan-Trang.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">PhDs in Logic XIII, Turin - Highlights from infinite games, mice, and their connection</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/2022/01/03/TalkPhDsInLogic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhDs in Logic XIII, Turin - Highlights from infinite games, mice, and their connection" /><published>2022-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/2022/01/03/TalkPhDsInLogic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/2022/01/03/TalkPhDsInLogic.html">&lt;p&gt;I am invited to give a talk at the PhDs in Logic XIII conference in Turin, Italy, September 5 - 7, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Highlights from infinite games, mice, and their connection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of inner models was initiated by Gödel’s analysis of the constructible universe. Later, the study of canonical inner models with large cardinals, e.g., measurable cardinals, strong cardinals or Woodin cardinals, was pioneered by Jensen, Mitchell, Steel, and others. Around the same time, the study of infinite two-player games was driven forward by Martin’s proof of analytic determinacy from a measurable cardinal, Borel determinacy from ZFC, and Martin and Steel’s proof of levels of projective determinacy from Woodin cardinals with a measurable cardinal on top. First Woodin and later Neeman improved the result in the projective hierarchy by showing that in fact the existence of a countable iterable model, a mouse, with Woodin cardinals and a top measure suffices to prove determinacy in the projective hierarchy. This opened up the possibility for an optimal result stating the equivalence between local determinacy hypotheses and the existence of mice in the projective hierarchy. In this talk, we will outline the main concepts and results connecting determinacy hypotheses with the existence of mice with large cardinals as well as recent progress in the area.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="upcomingtalk" /><category term="talk" /><category term="invconftalk" /><summary type="html">I am invited to give a talk at the PhDs in Logic XIII conference in Turin, Italy, September 5 - 7, 2022. Highlights from infinite games, mice, and their connection The study of inner models was initiated by Gödel’s analysis of the constructible universe. Later, the study of canonical inner models with large cardinals, e.g., measurable cardinals, strong cardinals or Woodin cardinals, was pioneered by Jensen, Mitchell, Steel, and others. Around the same time, the study of infinite two-player games was driven forward by Martin’s proof of analytic determinacy from a measurable cardinal, Borel determinacy from ZFC, and Martin and Steel’s proof of levels of projective determinacy from Woodin cardinals with a measurable cardinal on top. First Woodin and later Neeman improved the result in the projective hierarchy by showing that in fact the existence of a countable iterable model, a mouse, with Woodin cardinals and a top measure suffices to prove determinacy in the projective hierarchy. This opened up the possibility for an optimal result stating the equivalence between local determinacy hypotheses and the existence of mice in the projective hierarchy. In this talk, we will outline the main concepts and results connecting determinacy hypotheses with the existence of mice with large cardinals as well as recent progress in the area.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">European Set Theory Conference, Turin - Universally Baire Sets and the Inner Model Program</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/plenary/2022/01/02/TalkESTC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="European Set Theory Conference, Turin - Universally Baire Sets and the Inner Model Program" /><published>2022-01-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/plenary/2022/01/02/TalkESTC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/upcomingtalk/talk/invconftalk/plenary/2022/01/02/TalkESTC.html">&lt;p&gt;I am invited to give a &lt;b&gt;plenary talk&lt;/b&gt; at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://logicgroup.altervista.org/torino/ESTC2022/index.html&quot;&gt;European Set Theory Conference 2022&lt;/a&gt; in Turin, Italy, August 29 - September 2, 2022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Universally Baire Sets and the Inner Model Program&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universally Baire sets originate in work of Schilling and Vaught, and they were first systematically studied by Feng, Magidor, and Woodin. Since then they play a prominent role in many areas of set theory. We will discuss recent progress on their relationship to the Inner Model Program. First, we will outline the resolution of Sargsyan’s Conjecture on the large cardinal strength of determinacy when all sets are universally Baire. The second part of the talk will focus on sealing the theory of the universally Baire sets.
Woodin showed in his famous Sealing Theorem that in the presence of a proper class of Woodin cardinals $\mathsf{Sealing}$, a generic absoluteness principle for the theory of the universally Baire sets of reals, holds after collapsing a supercompact cardinal. We will outline the importance of $\mathsf{Sealing}$ and discuss a new and stationary-tower-free proof of Woodin’s Sealing Theorem that is based on Sargsyan’s and Trang’s proof of $\mathsf{Sealing}$ from iterability. The second part is joint work with Grigor Sargsyan and Bartosz Wcisło.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="upcomingtalk" /><category term="talk" /><category term="invconftalk" /><category term="plenary" /><summary type="html">I am invited to give a plenary talk at the European Set Theory Conference 2022 in Turin, Italy, August 29 - September 2, 2022. Universally Baire Sets and the Inner Model Program Universally Baire sets originate in work of Schilling and Vaught, and they were first systematically studied by Feng, Magidor, and Woodin. Since then they play a prominent role in many areas of set theory. We will discuss recent progress on their relationship to the Inner Model Program. First, we will outline the resolution of Sargsyan’s Conjecture on the large cardinal strength of determinacy when all sets are universally Baire. The second part of the talk will focus on sealing the theory of the universally Baire sets. Woodin showed in his famous Sealing Theorem that in the presence of a proper class of Woodin cardinals $\mathsf{Sealing}$, a generic absoluteness principle for the theory of the universally Baire sets of reals, holds after collapsing a supercompact cardinal. We will outline the importance of $\mathsf{Sealing}$ and discuss a new and stationary-tower-free proof of Woodin’s Sealing Theorem that is based on Sargsyan’s and Trang’s proof of $\mathsf{Sealing}$ from iterability. The second part is joint work with Grigor Sargsyan and Bartosz Wcisło.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">(with P. Lücke) Sigma_1-definability at higher cardinals: Thin sets, almost disjoint families and long well-orders</title><link href="https://muellersandra.github.io/publication/submitted/richterv844/loreal/2021/10/05/PaperSigma1Definability.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="(with P. Lücke) Sigma_1-definability at higher cardinals: Thin sets, almost disjoint families and long well-orders" /><published>2021-10-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://muellersandra.github.io/publication/submitted/richterv844/loreal/2021/10/05/PaperSigma1Definability</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://muellersandra.github.io/publication/submitted/richterv844/loreal/2021/10/05/PaperSigma1Definability.html">&lt;p&gt;Submitted. &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2110.01468.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.01468&quot;&gt;arXiv.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a data-toggle=&quot;collapse&quot; href=&quot;javascript:toggle('bibML21');&quot; class=&quot;title&quot;&gt;Bibtex.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display:none&quot; id=&quot;bibML21&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;collapse&quot;&gt; @ARTICLE{ML21,
   AUTHOR = {S. Müller and P. Lücke},
   TITLE = {Sigma_1-definability at higher cardinals: Thin sets, almost disjoint families and long well-orders},
   Note = {Submitted},
   EPRINT = {2110.01468}}&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given an uncountable cardinal $\kappa$, we consider the question whether
subsets of the power set of $\kappa$ that are usually constructed with the help
of the Axiom of Choice are definable by $\Sigma_1$-formulas that only use the
cardinal $\kappa$ and sets of hereditary cardinality less than $\kappa$ as
parameters. For limits of measurable cardinals, we prove a “perfect set
theorem” for sets definable in this way and use it to generalize two classical
non-definability results to higher cardinals. First, we show that a classical
result of Mathias on the complexity of maximal almost disjoint families of sets
of natural numbers can be generalized to measurable limits of measurables.
Second, we prove that for a limit of countably many measurable cardinals, the
existence of a simply definable well-ordering of subsets of $\kappa$ of length
at least $\kappa^+$ implies the existence of a projective well-ordering of the
reals. In addition, we determine the exact consistency strength of the
non-existence of $\Sigma_1$-definitions of certain objects at singular strong
limit cardinals. Finally, we show that both large cardinal assumptions and
forcing axioms cause analogs of these statements to hold at $\omega_1$.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="publication" /><category term="submitted" /><category term="RichterV844" /><category term="LOREAL" /><summary type="html">Submitted. PDF. arXiv. Bibtex. @ARTICLE{ML21, AUTHOR = {S. Müller and P. Lücke}, TITLE = {Sigma_1-definability at higher cardinals: Thin sets, almost disjoint families and long well-orders}, Note = {Submitted}, EPRINT = {2110.01468}}</summary></entry></feed>